John Muller Research Notes 148
People's Archive, MLK Library
John Muller Research Notes Collection
1869-2012
People's Archive, MLK Library
148
0.5 Cubic Feet
The John Muller Research Notes Collection documents John Muller's research for the book Frederick Douglass: The Lion of Anacostia published in 2012. Files include copies of Douglass' letters, speeches, speeches by others, pamphlets, and biographies of figures Douglass was close to.
Biographical / Historical
This collection contains the research conducted by John Muller for his book Frederick Douglass: The Lion of Anacostia published in 2012. Frederick Douglass spent his last two decades of life in Washington, D.C. Muller explores how Douglass spent his life, professionally and personally in his Anacostia home, Cedar Hill. The ever-active Douglass was involved in local politics: from aiding in the early formation of Howard University to editing a groundbreaking newspaper to serving as marshal of the District. This will be the first work to look into Douglass' years as a leading citizen of Uniontown when he served as US Marshal, Trustee to Howard University, was a frequent presence at Metropolitan African Methodist Episcopal Church, and shook up his family and society by marrying Helen Pitts in 1884. During this time, his wife of 44 years, Anna Murray, passed away, and 18 months later, he married Helen Pitts, a white woman. Douglass continued his advocacy for the rights of African Americans and women. Douglass attended a church in Hillsdale until the evening of his death on February 20, 1895.
Custodial History
Gift of John Muller, 2013.
Scope and Contents
The John Muller Research Notes Collection documents John Muller's research for the book Frederick Douglass: The Lion of Anacostia published in 2012. Files include copies of Douglass' letters, speeches, speeches by others, pamphlets, and biographies of figures Douglass was close to.
- Series 1
  - Anacostia Historic District Pamphlet, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Neighborhood News - Visiting Fredrick Douglass House, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Frederick Douglass - the Lion of Anacostia Flyers, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Frederick Douglass' Washington: The Lion of Anacostia Text/Draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mark Twain Project, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Frederick Douglass Papers Vol. Speeches and Lectures John Blassingame, 1871-1875 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - David Turk Speech - Cedar Hill 2/14/2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Excerpts: Bios/Autobios Ida B. Wells/Mary Church Terrell/Mary Ann Shadd Cary/Josiah Henson, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters - Frederick Douglass - Papers - Library of Congress, 1869-1895 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 2 Letters from Howard University 7/18/2012 8/6/2012 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - R.B Hayes Files - Douglass Vertical Files, 1977-1881 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Have We a Cause: The Life of Helen Pitts Douglass 1837-1903 by Julie R. Nelson, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)